<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Classical Music | a programmer having fun with bits]]></title>
  <link href="http://funwithbits.net/blog/categories/classical-music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://funwithbits.net/"/>
  <updated>2021-01-29T16:04:05-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://funwithbits.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raphael S. Carvalho (a.k.a. utroz)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programming and Classical Music]]></title>
    <link href="http://funwithbits.net/blog/programming-and-classical-music/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-16T00:03:39-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://funwithbits.net/blog/programming-and-classical-music</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s some magic about classical music that helps me as a programmer.
Well, I&rsquo;m definitely not the best programmer out there, so when I find it hard
to come up with a creative solution, I listen to classical music over and over
again.
I leave my gratitude here for Chopin, Mozart, Dvorak, Paganini, Vivaldi,
Beethoven and so many others composers. I&rsquo;m so grateful for all those pieces
you guys have left behind.
When I&rsquo;m going through a creativity crisis, I listen to their songs. I also
like to listen to them while working. It can be said that we all need to be
in a good mood to produce quality work. That&rsquo;s another thing that classical
music plays an important role in my life. Whatever my mood is, I listen to
classical music because it impacts my mind in a good manner. It&rsquo;s almost like
an infinite potion of inspiration that you can drink from.</p>

<p>People have different tastes, so I was thinking if your favorite genre can
have the same effect on your life. Classical rock, instrumental rock, etc,
could work too. But I don&rsquo;t think shitty, noisy pop music will do it.
I actually don&rsquo;t think I can find the same level of magic in Beethoven
symphonies, Vivaldi&rsquo;s four seasons, Paganini&rsquo;s caprices, etc, in some other
genre. The complexity of the melody, the depth, the harmony in those musics are
outstanding. I&rsquo;m having a really hard time here to describe it, i.e. how
classical music impacts almost every single aspect of my life. It helps me
boosting my creativity and also keeping focused on the most important things,
it makes me happy when I&rsquo;m sad, and also the other way around. Yes, the
latter is true, have you ever tried listening to Chopin and Beethoven&rsquo;s
sonatas?</p>

<p>If you aren&rsquo;t into classical music, I leave here my invitation for you to try
it out. I will help you get started by leaving some links below to some musics
from the composers I like the most. These are just the tip of the iceberg
though.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll start with a magical performance by the Brazilian musician Arthur Moreira
Lima which is considered one of the best Chopin interpreters:
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QmF2F8YBU3E" title="Click to watch"><img src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/QmF2F8YBU3E/0.jpg" alt="IMAGE ALT TEXT" /></a></p>

<p>Now Beethoven&rsquo;s moonlight sonata played by the brilliant piano player Valentina
Lisitsa:
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zucBfXpCA6s" title="Click to watch"><img src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/zucBfXpCA6s/0.jpg" alt="IMAGE ALT TEXT" /></a></p>

<p>I really hope you guys will give classical music a chance. I didn&rsquo;t listen to
it when I was a teenager. Now I love it, it&rsquo;s my favorite genre by far. Anyone
out there that share the same feelings? Not necessarily due to classical music,
but whichever genre you like the most.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
